

Curriculum Vitae for Ada Ortiz-Carbonell

Personal information

Address: Colletts gate 59 E-mail: ada@xal.no

0456 - Oslo Phone: +47 98887847

Born: 7^{th} January 1975

Summary

I hold a PhD in Physics from 2003 specializing in Solar Physics. Since then I have more than 15 years of experience in data mining, image analysis, time-series analysis and spectral analysis. With time I have expanded my research subjects and used different methods including statistical data analysis and signal processing.

I consider myself very perseverant and used to overcome adversity in a scientific environment by being creative, hard-working, and having an analytical mindset. Excellence, accuracy and detail define my scientific work. I have well-proven organisational capabilities. My colleagues regard me as an excellent communicator and an all-terrain asset. I have experience in leading international collaborations, management of grants, student mentoring and scientific outreach. I consider myself a responsible and organised team player.

Technical skills

Languages IDL, Fortran, LaTeX in a Unix and Mac OS X environment

Scientific skills Image analysis, pattern recognition, anomaly detection, analysis of

time series, analytical modelling, statistical analysis

Tools Mac OS X and Unix

Education

2000 - 2003	PhD in Physics. University of Barcelona (Spain). Thesis title: "Solar
	irradiance variations induced by faculae and small magnetic elements
	in the photosphere". Cum Laude by unanimity.
1997 - 2000	Research Proficiency. University of Barcelona (Spain)
1993 - 1997	Licentiate in Physics. University of Barcelona (Spain)

Professional experience

2000 - 2003	PhD student. University of Barcelona (Spain). Appointment inclu-
	ding 25% teaching/administration and 75% research training.
2004 - 2006	Postdoctoral fellow. High Altitude Observatory, National Center for
	Atmospheric Research,(Boulder, USA)
2007 - 2010	Postdoctoral fellow. Institute of Theoretical Astrophysics, University
	of Oslo, (Norway)
2013 - 2014	Lecturer. Institute of Theoretical Astrophysics, University of Oslo,
	(Norway)
2010 - 2019	Researcher. Institute of Theoretical Astrophysics, University of Oslo,
	(Norway)
2019 –	Data scientist. Expert Analytics (Oslo, Norway)

Languages

Catalan mother tongue

English fluent

Italian intermediate

Norwegian basic

Spanish mother tongue

Personal skills

Analitycal ability to tackle the unknown by collecting the necessary information, thinking analyzing and interpreting it, obtaining results using cross-disciplinary

methods, and present them in an easy-to-understand manner. Orga-

nisation and planning of tasks.

Communication regarded by my peers as an excellent speaker, both in scientific talks to and writing an specialized audience or in educating the public. Proven experience

skills in writing scientific articles and documents.

Complex apply creativity to break down complex problems into smaller parts that can be tackled in an easier way, but keeping the big picture in solving mind at the same time. Combine methods from different disciplines

(or learning new ones) to solve problems.

Leadership experience as project leader and manager of research grants in inter-

national collaborations. Also comfortable as team member where I am

organized, structured and a responsible player.

Organizational we

skills

well-proven experience as organizer for several international conferences and schools, where I have done everything from managing the

logistical aspects, setting up the conference's websites and planning

the scientific programmes.

Teaching and experience as Lecturer at the University of Oslo. Ability to explain outreach difficult material and break it down in an understandable language for

the non-expert. Significant experience in outreach explaining complex science to the general public and engaging them into the wonders of

the Universe.

Versatile and I feel comfortable whether it is scientific, administration, logistics,

all-terrain organisation or managing tasks.

Some interests and hobbies

Scientific outreach officer in Norway for the European Solar Telescope project, outreach Astronomy on Tap (astronomy for the general public), and scientific

talks for the general public

Sports Alpine skiing, scuba diving, martial arts, white-water rafting

Extended descriptions of selected projects

Activity Observing and understanding flux emergence using IRIS and SST coor-

dinated data. Research project funded by the Research Council of Nor-

way.

Role Project leader

Staffing 2 members and 5 collaborators

Description this effort aimed at studying how magnetic fields living in the interior

of the Sun rise up and trespass the surface of the star while continuing their journey up through the solar atmosphere. The project involves combining big data sets (images and spectra) both from space and ground-based observatories, image analysis, spectral analysis across several wavelengths ranges, student mentoring, statistical analysis, and

comparison with numerical simulations.

Activity Space and ground-based observations of the solar atmosphere. Rese-

arch project funded by the Research Council of Norway.

Role Project leader and grant holder

Staffing me, with 4 collaborators

Description the goal of this project was to study the lower part of the solar atmos-

phere at the highest spatial resolution, in order to see the smallest details ever seen on the surface of a star. Both the dynamics and magnetism of the physical processes going on in the surface were studied. The project involved the analysis of big data sets of images and spectra, time series, data reduction (cleaning the data from instrumental affects and make it ready-to-use), feature tracking algorithms,

and statistical data analysis.

Activity Science communication and outreach. Norwegian EST Communica-

tion Officer.

Role member of organising committee

expertanalytics.no

Staffing 4 members

Description organize and manage a series of posts in the social media about the

Sun and the European Solar Telescope project to educate the general public about the importance of studying our nearest star. Also in charge of the outreach and education activities in Norway related to

the EST project.

Activity Human resources and administration, hiring committee at the Institute

of Theoretical Astrophysics (University of Oslo).

Role member Staffing 3-5 members

Description evaluate and interview candidates for the open positions at the Insti-

tute, from PhD students to postdoctoral fellows and researchers.

Activity Organisation of international conferences and schools

Role co-organizer Staffing 2 members

Description I have organised 7 schools and international conferences since 2010.

My tasks involved everything from planning the scientific programme, managing the logistical aspects, being in charge of the conference's websites and designing the logos and banners. In addition to these, I have been convener of 2 symposia (part of big astronomical meetings with ± 10000 attendants) were I was responsible for the scientific pro-

gramme.

Activity European Solar Telescope Science Advisory Group member. Infrastruc-

ture and technological project funded by the European Union H2020

Framework and national funding agencies.

Role core member Staffing 21 members

Description define and evaluate the scientific questions that will be tackled by

the next generation 4 meter class European Solar Telescope. This project is an infrastructure, technological and scientific challenge of pan-European dimensions involving 16 countries and 23 scientific institutions. Budget = 200 MEuros. Our task is to envision the questions about the Sun that will be interesting in 10 years and design the in-

strumentation that will be necessary to tackle those questions.